OK בוקר טוב, boker tov, we start today, today's דף daf is
נג, nun gimmel, we start on the bottom of נב עמוד ב,
nun bet amud bet, and we are במקום
שאין מצילין אין דרוסה.
bemakom she-ein
matzilin ein derusah. It is five lines down to the wide line.
Beginning of the words are אין דרוסה. ein derusah. OK, so the
issue here had been that we introduced these smaller animals that we
said could do an act of דרוסה, derusah, could basically make the
when they
attack the small animal like a sheep or goat, would make it
a טרפה treifah because of this concern of דרוסה, derusah, which was
a concern of poison and the like. Joe's next.
Come around from this side so you don't see all the wiring.
All right. Anyway. And the issue was
that OK, fine, he says he can't get up. Anyway. And the
issue was that what do you call the issue was that the
גמרא Gemara ah, so so see these smaller animals like a cat
or a weasel and so on, but the problem was that the
משנה Mishnah only mentioned a slightly larger animal which was
a wolf. So the גמרא Gemara said, well, no, these would work
with smaller animals like baby sheep or baby goats or whatever. And
then we had a ברייתא Brayta that said that even these animals
did not do an act of דרוסה, derusah, did not have insert
their poison, was not a problem. And it says the problem is
that the OK, so we'll reconcile by saying that when these animals
are feeling that the prey is going to be saved, then they
attack more viciously and then they insert their poison. OK, let's see
what the גמרא Gemara now does with that. It says the following.
Where are we? במקום שאין מצילין אין דרוסה. bemakom she-ein matzilin ein
derusah. Are
you telling me that when they're not afraid that their prey will
be saved, they don't do an act of דרוסה? derusah? וההיא תרנגולת
דהוה בי רב כהנא. ve-hahi tarnegolet de-hava bei Rav Kahana. There was
a chicken in the house of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. דרט חתול
בתרה. de-rat chatul batrah. That a cat was chasing after it. ועל
לאינדרא. ve-al le-indara. And it went into a room.
OK? I guess the cat chased the chicken into a room. It's
very interesting, אינדרא indara is not such a common ארמית Aramaic word.
If you look at the side in the right hand margin, it
says תרגום של ויבוא יהודה ויבוא
החדר ויבך שם Targum shel vayavo Yehudah vayavo hachadar vayevk sham by
יוסף Yosef as ועל לאינדרא. ve-al le-indara. So interesting quoting an אונקלוס
Onkelos to help you who's very helpful to help you translate this
obscure ארמית Aramaic word. I still remember many years ago when I
was doing שנים מקרא אחד תרגום shenayim mikra echad Targum and I
got to that פסוק pasuk ועל לאינדרא. ve-al le-indara. Obviously I could
have figured it out by context, but I remember that I also
had to look that up. What the heck is an אינדרא? indara?
Anyway, so it went into an inner chamber. It's like into a
room. ואיטחיד דשא באפי. ve-itchid dasha be-appei.
The door was slammed in its presence. So there it was, this
cat was alone with a chicken in the bedroom in the room.
OK. ומחיה לדשא בסיחופיה u-machya le-dasha be-sichufei
and it smote against the door, thank you, with its claws. The
cat, apparently. ואשתכח עלה חמשה קורטי דמא. ve-ishtakach alah chamisha kurtei dema.
And there were five drops of blood, apparently one for each claw.
I don't know, does a cat have five fingers? Anyway, there were
five drops of blood, whatever it was, on the door. So you
see, apparently those drops of blood are an indication of the type
of poison that it injects. And here it was, nothing could have
saved this chicken from the cat because it was alone in a
room. So why was it why was it injecting its poison? You
see it injects its poison even if there's nothing that will save
its prey. So the גמרא Gemara says הצלת עצמה נמי כהצלת אחרינא
דמי. hatzalat atzmah nami ke-hatzalat acharina dami. No,
there it was afraid not that the chicken would be saved, but
it was afraid that somebody would enter into the room and try
to, you know the cat itself was somehow being threatened. It knew
why go to a room? Because it knew that people were running
after it. So therefore it was in the process of trying to
like protect itself and therefore it was also the poison was coursing
through its system. All right. Whatever. So now the גמרא Gemara says
רבנן זיעה ראיתה. Rabanan zei'ah ra'itah. What do the רבנן Rabanan say
if they say that even the small animals
never do דרוסה? derusah? How do they explain the blood that occurred
in this case with the cat? So they say it is true
it does have some poison, ולא קלי זיקיה. ve-lo kali zikei. But
its poison does not burn. So basically, yeah, it has poison, but
it's not enough to do the job. OK, so anyway,
here you have the issue about the claim that these small animals
can do a type of what do you call it can do
a type
of דרוסה, derusah, of attacking which would cause death or poison under
the right circumstances that they're that they're feeling that they're being attacked
or they're going to be intervened and that they're a small enough
prey. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on, and it says basically the
same thing except in reverse.
But at the time of the גמרא, Gemara, they're familiar with these
animals. I mean, wouldn't you think they knew that they didn't have
poison?
Well, I think that they saw that at times animals died as
a result and they didn't know how to explain it. And so
they, you know, if you don't if you don't have modern science,
you, you know, you come up with your own ad
hoc... had very little to do with snake poison, you know, but
that was their explanation of it. Okay. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. איכא דאמרי Ika
De'amri some say. So basically the same thing except a different ברייתא.
Braita. המני ברבי היא? Hamani B'Rebbi Hi? This is the position of
רבי. Rebbi. The idea is that these small animals can do דריסה
derisa because we taught רבי אומר לא אמרו יש דריסה אלא במקום
שיש מצילן. Rebbi Omer Lo Amru Yesh Derisa Ela B'makom Sheyesh Matzilin.
אבל במקום שאין מצילן Aval B'makom She'ein Matzilin אין דריסה. Ein Derisa.
I'm sorry. The statement that these small animals do not do דריסה
derisa is רבי. Rebbi. Because רבי Rebbi says: when did they say
these small animals do דריסה? derisa? Only if there is no animal
to intervene but there's no they're not going to be the prey
will not there'll be nobody to intervene for the prey. But if
some the animals are concerned that somebody will intervene for the prey,
then I'm sorry, did I misread that? They only said that there
is דריסה derisa when they're afraid somebody was somebody will intervene and
to protect the prey. But when they're not afraid, then they're not
as vicious and there's no דריסה. derisa. So it's exactly the same
statement. The only difference is the implication of what the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma said. ברבי Bi'Rebbi is always saying that these animals will
insert their poison when they're afraid somebody will intervene, not when they
won't. But the first statement made it sound like the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma said that that he was arguing against the position of
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that said that there's never דריסה. derisa. Here
it sounds like he's arguing against the position of תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma that said that there's always דריסה. derisa. Okay. So so the
question is, we had a position that these small animals had דריסה,
derisa, so the first version was, oh, that was ברבי Bi'Rebbi who
says they have דריסה derisa when it's יש מצילן. yesh matzilin. Now
we're saying the reverse. The position that said יש דריסה, yesh derisa,
that's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says always
with these small animals יש דריסה. yesh derisa. The position that said
that there's no דריסה derisa by these animals, that's רבי, Rebbi, and
that's in a case where they're not being vicious, where there's nobody
intervening. It boils down to the same thing. The only question is
whether the תנא which position the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is saying.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ובמקום שאין מצילן אין דריסה? U'v'makom She'ein Matzilin Ein Derisa? Are
you telling me that when there is nobody to intervene there's no
דריסה? derisa? And now we're claiming that everybody says that the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma I'm sorry, that's sorry that רבי Rebbi says that
when there's nobody to intervene. והא ההיא תרנגולת דהוה בי רב כהנא
דרהט חתולא בתרה ועל לאינדרונא ואישתחיד דשא באפי מאכלי ודשה
בסיקופיה ושחטוה וחמשה קורטי דמא? Ve'ha hee tarnigolta d'hava bei Rav Kahana
d'rahat chatula batra ve'al le'indrona ve'ishtachid dasha b'apei machlei v'dasha b'sikufei v'shachtuha
v'chamisha kurtei dama? So the same story with the cat running after
the chicken. So there you see that there was nobody intervening and
that there was and there was this poison. So how could רבי
Rebbi say that there is not this poison when there's nobody intervening?
So the גמרא Gemara says: כהצלת עצמן נמי כהצלת אחרים דמיא. K'hatzalat
atzman nami k'hatzalat acherim damya. No, it was protecting itself and therefore
it was, you know, the poison was coursing through its system. Okay,
so anyway, that was a little bit of wrapping up of yesterday,
which is basically saying that the משנה Mishna speaks that for small
animals, maybe for תנא קמא for all animals, a a wolf can
create דריסה. derisa. Now we have introduced the idea of these smaller
things can create דריסה, derisa, the חתול, chatul, the cat, the חולדה,
chulda, the weasel, but that but when it's attacking small animals like
baby sheep, baby goat. That's contradicted. There are other versions that it
doesn't. And we say some of this is debated and some of
it depends whether the animal is afraid of intervention and how much
therefore it will be vicious and use its poison. Okay. בעי מיניה
רב כהנא מרב. Ba'ei minei Rav Kahana mi'Rav. Now moving on to
נג, Nun Gimmel, רב כהנא Rav Kahana asked רב, Rav, top of
נג עמוד א. Nun Gimmel Amud Aleph. יש דריסה לחתול או אין
דריסה לחתול? Yesh derisa l'chatul o ein derisa l'chatul? Now it seems
to be the exact same question we had before, whether cats create
דריסה. derisa. Before we said it could do it with small animals
perhaps if it was, you know, based on the debate whether it
was afraid of intervention or not. Anyway, here we have a series
of questions that רב כהנא Rav Kahana asked רב, Rav, and רב
Rav gave him very like Yoda-like answers or something. So let's take
a look. He says: is there דריסה derisa for the cat or
not דריסה derisa for a cat? אמר ליה אף
לחולדה יש דריסה. Amar lei af l'chulda yesh derisa. What, why are
you asking about a cat? Even a weasel, which is smaller, creates
דריסה. derisa. So then he says to him: okay, יש דריסה לחולדה
או אין דריסה לחולדה? Yesh derisa l'chulda o ein derisa l'chulda?
Is there דריסה derisa for a weasel? אמר ליה אף לחתול אין
דריסה.
Amar
lei af l'chatul ein derisa.
I just answered that, but he wanted to clarify it. Maybe he
was saying like like so anyway, let's see what he says. אמר
ליה אף לחתול אין דריסה. Amar lei af l'chatul ein derisa. What
a stupid question! There isn't even דריסה derisa for a cat, so
why are you asking me for a weasel? So
then he says figured, okay, let's start try to get a straight
answer out of him. לחתול ולחולדה יש להן דריסה אין להן דריסה?
L'chatul u'l'chulda yesh lahen derisa ein lahen derisa? How about a cat
and a weasel? Do they have דריסה derisa or not? אמר ליה
לחתול יש דריסה לחולדה אין דריסה. Amar lei l'chatul yesh derisa l'chulda
ein derisa.
Yes for cat, no for weasel. So make up your mind! One
time you're answering no for both, the other time you say yes
for both, the other time you're splitting your vote. So the גמרא
Gemara says: ולא קשיא. V'lo kashya. It's not difficult. הא דאמר ליה
אף לחולדה יש דריסה. Ha d'amar lei af l'chulda yesh derisa. When
he said even for a weasel there is דריסה, derisa, בעופות, b'ofot,
that's when it's attacking birds. הא דאמר ליה אף לחתול אין דריסה,
Ha d'amar lei af l'chatul ein derisa, even for a cat דריסה
derisa if a cat does דריסה derisa it's not effective, באימרי רברבי,
b'imrei ravrevei, large sheep. הא דאמר ליה לחתול יש דריסה לחולדה אין
דריסה, Ha d'amar lei l'chatul yesh derisa l'chulda ein derisa, when he
split his vote for cat yes for weasel no, בגדיים וטלאים, bi'g'dayim
u't'layim, so when is that?
That's when you're talking about like baby goats, baby sheep. So those
types of things, those were what we had been discussing before, and
here he says. For cats yes, for weasels no, not distinguishing in
any case about whether they think they're going to be intervened or
not. So it depends on the size not only of the attacker,
but the size of the prey, we already saw that in the
משנה, Mishna, and here in the משנה Mishna there was a distinction
made maybe between you know cows versus goats and goats versus birds.
Here we're distinguishing, we added a third category which is baby sheep,
baby goats. So for sheep, for birds, both of these the answer
is no. For large sheep and large goats the answer for both
of these, I'm sorry, for birds the answer both is yes. Large
sheep and large goats both is no. And for baby sheep, baby
goats it splits between a cat and a weasel. Yes.
But in רב's Rav's answer it depends.
Yes, so that's what תוספות Tosafot says. So תוספות Tosafot has a
couple of explanations about how רב Rav was right, basically something along
those lines about why רב Rav was being so cryptic. You know
רב Rav was sort of saying: oh there are some things that
even works for both, there are some things that doesn't work for
any, you know, or whatever. Exactly. Exactly. Okay.
Never have a document share like that, yeah, that's what we got.
בעא רב אשי. Ba'ei Rav Ashi. So now רב אשי Rav Ashi
asked: שאר עופות טמאים יש להם דרוסה אין להם דרוסה? She'ar ofot
tmei'im yesh lahem drusa ein lahem drusa? How about other non-kosher birds?
Our משנה Mishna mentioned now, now we're talking about birds attacking other
birds, right? Because until now we've said that the only you know
small animals might be able to do דרוסה drusa against small animals
or against birds, but birds until now can only have attack other
birds in terms of this הלכה halacha of creating דרוסה. drusa. So
our משנה Mishna mentioned the נץ, netz, which is the sparrowhawk, and
the גס, gas, which is the buzzard. Okay, but what about other
birds? Can other birds that other birds of prey that attack other
birds? Like a vulture, yeah, right, exactly, other birds of prey that
attack other birds, will that create דרוסה drusa or not? So let's
take a look. אמר ליה רב הילל לרב אשי, Amar leih Rav
Hillel le-Rav Ashi, כי הוינא בי רב כהנא אמרי, ki havina bei
Rav Kahana amri, what I was in the house of רב כהנא
Rav Kahana he
said: שאר עופות טמאים יש להם דרוסה, She'ar ofot tmei'im yesh lahem
drusa, other non-kosher birds do, other birds of prey do create דרוסה.
drusa. So what do you mean? והאנן תנן ודרוסת הנץ בעוף דק
ודרוסת הנץ. Ve-hanan tnan u-drusat ha-netz be-of dak u-drusat ha-netz. So it
says only the sparrowhawk by small birds, so presumably to exclude other
birds. So again, like we had before when we dealt with the
זאב, ze'ev, we weren't excluding other things, we're only excluding smaller things,
bigger, you know, animals of prey certainly would. So here too the
answer is similar. So let's see what he says.
דרוסת הנץ בדכוותיה, Drusat ha-netz bidekhvateih, a sparrowhawk creates דרוסה drusa even
in a bird of similar size. ואינך, Ve-inakh, other birds of prey,
בדזוטרו מיניה, bedizutru mineih, will only create דרוסה drusa of birds of
smaller size, not of equal size. Okay, so again the size of
the prey is relevant as well. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, others say,
so the answer is why our משנה Mishna mentioned sparrowhawk was to
say a sparrowhawk creates דרוסה drusa even of birds of comparable size.
Other birds of prey will create דרוסה drusa but only of birds
of smaller size.
Right. But what about a bird of a larger size? There's no
way?
No for either. However, איכא דאמרי, ika de-amri, others say, דרוסת הנץ
בדראבי מיניה, drusat ha-netz bidarabi mineih, a sparrowhawk can create דרוסה drusa
even by larger birds. ואינך, Ve-inakh, other birds of prey, בדכוותיה, bidekhvateih,
will only create דרוסה drusa by equivalent sized birds. So clearly the
sparrowhawk is more, has greater ability to create דרוסה, drusa, but the
question is does that create even an equal size or even in
larger size. אמר רב כהנא משמיה דרב שימי בר אשי, Amar Rav
Kahana mishmeih de-Rav Shimi bar Ashi, אין דרוסה לשועל, ein drusa le-shual,
there is no דרוסה drusa for a fox. Okay, we've been talking
about a זאב, ze'ev, a wolf, but for a fox that does
not create דרוסה. drusa. If a fox attacks an animal. איני, Ini,
is that really true? Which is pretty amazing considering that we just
said that a cat and a weasel can create דרוסה drusa if
it's a small enough prey, so to say not a fox? But
again remember if the concern was this belief of some poison, so
maybe even if an animal does you know create a serious gouge,
it might not inject this poison, and that's the concern. Okay, so
let's take a look.
Very interesting because רב כהנא Rav Kahana is the one that always
asks questions of רב, Rav, he seems to know the answer of
so many of the other ones.
That's interesting, maybe he knew this answer but he knew this from
the name of רב שימי, Rav Shimi, maybe he knew this because
he was asked, he asked a lot of people, so then he
collected this wisdom. Okay, so anyway, אין דרוסה לשועל, ein drusa le-shual,
is this really true? וכי אתא רב דימי, ve-khi ata Rav Dimi,
when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר
מעשה בשועל ורחל במרחץ, amar ma'aseh be-shual ve-rachel be-mirkhatz, there's a story
that a fox attacked a sheep in a, you know, a ewe
in a bathhouse, של בית היני, shel Beit Heini, in the place
of Beit Heini, ובא מעשה לפני חכמים ואמרו יש דרוסה, u-va ma'aseh
lifnei chakhamim ve-amru yesh drusa, and they came before the sages and
they said yeah there's the problem of דרוסה. drusa. So here you
have that at least a fox can create דרוסה drusa by small
sheep, similar to a cat and a weasel, makes sense. So how
you going to get out of this? So אמר רב ספרא, amar
Rav Safra, האי חתול הוה, hai chatul hava, that wasn't a fox,
that was a cat. So cats do it, foxes don't do it.
איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amri, others say, אמר רב כהנא משמיה דרב שימי
בר רב דימי, amar Rav Kahana mishmeih de-Rav Shimi bar Rav Dimi,
אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, יש דרוסה לשועל, yesh drusa le-shual,
that there is a דרוסה drusa for a fox. Again notice again
this big question about the accuracy of the tradition. Okay, the other
version was he said foxes don't have it, here he says foxes
do have it. איני, Ini, is this really true? וכי אתא רב
דימי, ve-khi ata Rav Dimi, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came, אמר
מעשה בשועל ורחל במרחץ של בית היני, amar ma'aseh be-shual ve-rachel be-mirkhatz
shel Beit Heini, there was a story where the where this again
this fox trampled a sheep in the in the bathhouse. of בית
היני. Beis Hini. ובא מעשה לפני חכמים ואמרו אין דריסה. Uva ma'aseh
lifnei chachamim ve'amru ein derisah. And it came before the sages and
they said there is not a דריסה. derisah. So notice again, both
versions got reversed. Meaning here we're having the version that רב אשי
Rav Ashi actually said it is a problem and then when they
challenged him, the version is is that the story with this fox
and the bathhouse or whatever that the that the ruling was was
that it isn't a problem. Okay, so you have two versions, two
versions of what רב אשי Rav Ashi said, two versions about the
story of the bathhouse. So based on the version of what רב
אשי Rav Ashi said, they ask him from the other version of
the bathhouse story. Okay, so how can you say there is דריסה,
derisah, don't we have this bathhouse story where they said there wasn't
דריסה? derisah? So אמר רב ספרא ההוא כלבא הוה. amar Rav Safra
hahu kalba hava.
No, no one can get this straight at all.
Nobody can get it straight. That wasn't a fox, that was a
dog. So even if a fox has דריסה, derisah, a dog does
not. So again, the issue here and we're going to see, you
know, what do you mean, I mean a lot of people are
afraid about dogs biting them, so we're about to see that דריסה
derisah is not about biting. דריסה derisah is about clawing, which then
really makes sense, you know, that cats have claws, dogs don't really
have claws. It's about clawing. I don't know, fox, wolves are types
of are they types of dogs? Canines. What?
Foxes and wolves
are both types of dogs, right? Same basic, right. So it's pretty
funny that the משנה mishna fundamentally focuses on the wolves and here
there's a whole question about the fox. Okay, but we assume that
cats and weasels are worse because again it's an issue of clawing.
So clawing, you know, these other animals might attack viciously but they're
not clawing, and the specific concern here is clawing. So now let's
take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, אמר רב
יוסף, amar Rav Yosef,
Rav Yosef says, נקטינן, naktinan, we take as a sort of as
a position, meaning this is sort of our our general operating principle
is the following: אין דריסה לכלב, ein derisah lekelev, dogs do not
have דריסה. derisah. For the reason I said is as we're going
to see in a minute that דריסה derisah is about clawing, not
about biting. אמר אביי, amar Abaye, Abaye says נקטינן, naktinan, we take
as a sort of operating position, אין דריסה אלא ביד, ein derisah
ela beyad, דריסה derisah is only what it does with its forehand,
forehand, whatever, forearm, what it does with its with its you know
front with its front legs. לאפוקי רגל דלא, la'apukei regel dlo, if
it tramples on something with its foot, that's just stam pressure but
it's no none of this poison and therefore it's not a problem.
And not only that, אין דריסה אלא בציפורן, ein derisah ela betziporen,
it's only with its nails, with its claws. And now it makes
sense why we're excluding dogs. אבל לאפוקי שן דלא, aval la'apukei shen
dlo, attacking with its teeth not. Now again, what we have not
said yet but we will say again is if in any of
these attacks there's a concern that it really led to a puncture
of an inner organ, so then of course a puncture of an
inner organ if it came through a dog bite is a problem.
And if you're concerned that the dog bite led to a puncture
of the inner organ then you'll have to check to see if
it did lead to the puncture. So if it lead to a
different טריפה treifah problem like a puncture of an inner organ, that's
an issue. But here we're talking just by virtue of this itself.
The fact that it broke the skin, will we say that it
injected poison? It didn't break an inner organ, there's not a concern
of an inner organ, the concern is is that it clawed and
it broke the skin, did it inject this poison, this belief that
these animals have poison? So here we're saying it's only when it
uses its arm, you know there are some what animals do have
poison with their when they attack with their claw? Are there those
types of animals that actually inject poison with their claw? I mean
snakes do it with their bite, scorpions do it with their tail.
What type of animal other animals inject poison?
Bees with their stinger I guess. Does anybody know? Are there any
animals that have poison that comes from their claw? Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara assumes that these are poison that comes from their claw.
So therefore it limits it to when it's the front feet, right?
I mean animals that do have claws, right, like they have retractable
claws, that's their front feet, right, it's not their back feet. So
it is true in terms of the focus on the front and
the focus on the claw. The גמרא Gemara is just associating that
then with poison. Okay, it assumes that birds have it, birds of
prey, it assumes that these cats have it, it assumes wolves have
it, weasels have it, but with this assumption of poison it's saying
it's only the front hand and it's only certain animals and it's
only the claw and it's not the teeth. And these are the
ones you have to be afraid of.
Because snakes do it through the teeth, so you'd think that there'd
be more of a concern with the teeth than with the claw.
Right, I mean it does seem that there are these animals that
do have, you know, that do have particularly means of attacking through
their claw or talons, then somehow the גמרא Gemara just somehow assumes
that there was poison associated with it. So we're not done, let's
take a look.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, אין דריסה אלא בציפורן
לאפוקי שן דלא, ein derisah ela betziporen la'apukei shen dlo, אין דריסה
אלא מדעת, ein derisah ela mida'at,
and it's only when it happens like that the animal is consciously
attacking somebody with its claw. אבל לאפוקי שלא מדעת דלא, aval la'apukei
shelo mida'at dlo,
if let's say its claws were extended and it was just and
you know and it accidentally fell on another animal or an animal
fell on it then okay the claws would go in but the
poison wouldn't go. The poison only comes when the animal is consciously
attacking another animal.
Did you do a search which animals inject poison with their claw?
You know what comes up? What? חולין דף נב ונג. Chullin daf
fifty-two and fifty-three.
Yeah, it's pretty funny. We'll check it out.
Just Google, yeah, that's pretty funny.
Okay, okay.
Okay, so only if it does it knowingly. אין *ein* דרוסה drusah
*derusa* אלא *ella* מחיים me-chayyim *michayim* לאפוקי *la'apoke* לאחר *le'achar* מיתה *misa*
דלא *delo*. Only if it does it while it's alive, not if
a dead animal with its extended claw fell on another animal. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, אמרי *amri*, השתא *hashta* שלא
*shelo* מדעת *mada'as* אמרת *amarta* לא *lo*, if you said that when
the animal is alive and it doesn't knowingly claw another animal there's
no
poison, לאחר *le'achar*
מיתה *misa* מיבעיא *mibaya*, of course if it's dead it won't inject
its poison. Ah very good.
לא *lo* צריכא *tzricha* דדרס *de-daras*, that it basically had clawed an
animal, ופסקיה *u-paskle* לידיה *le-yadei*, and then the hand was cut off.
So the animal isn't dead, but its hand is basically dead. Okay.
מהו *mahu* דתימא *de-teima* בהדי *be-hade* דדרס *de-daras* שדי *shadi* זיהריה *zeharei*,
I might think that in the process of clawing and inserting the
claws, it injected its poison even though now it has died or
its hand has been cut off. קא *ka* משמע mashma *mashma* לן
*lan* בהדי *be-hade* דשליף *de-shalif* שדי *shadi* זיהריה *zeharei*, its poison only
gets injected as it removes its claw. So not while it claws
into the animal, but as it pulls out its claw, that's when
the poison gets deposited. אמר *amar* רבה *Rabbah* בר *bar* אבונא *Avuna*
אמר *amar* רב Rav *Rav*. So now, okay, now we've understood when
we are concerned that the concern is very explicit in this גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* it's about poison, it's about claws, and now we understand
why cats and weasels presumably more than dogs, we don't, I wouldn't
exactly understand why wolves more than foxes. Anyway, now we are going
on.
Okay. אמר *amar* רבה *Rabbah* בר *bar* אבונא *Avuna* אמר *amar* רב
Rav? *Rav*. ארי *ari* שנכנס *she-nichnas* לבין *le-vein* השוורים *ha-shvarim*, a lion
goes between oxen. ונמצאת *ve-nimtza* ציפורן *tziporen* בגבו *be-gavlo* של *shel* אחד
*echad* מהם *me-hem*, and now you find afterwards a lion finger or
claw, not a finger, a claw, whatever, a fingernail, excuse me, sticking
out of the back of one of the oxen. Okay, so what
assumption should we make? Presumably that it clawed that ox, and that
ox at least is a דרוסה drusah. *derusa*, טריפה treifah *treifa*. So
let's take a look.
So אין *ein* חוששין chosheshin, *chosheshin* שמא *shema* ארי *ari* דרסו *deraso*,
we are not concerned that the lion clawed it. מאי *mai* טעמא
*ta'ama*, what's the reason? רוב *rov* אריות *arayos* דורסין *dorsin*, it is
true that the majority of lions will have the capacity of doing
דריסה *derisa*. תוספות Tosfos, *Tosfos* says not that they do דריסה *derisa*
in any given moment, but they have the capacity. ומיעוטן *u-mi'utan* אין
*ein* דורסין *dorsin*, there is a minority that are, you know, not
vicious or whatever or sick and don't, will not do דריסה *derisa*.
So just because a lion was there doesn't necessarily mean that it
was, that it had the capacity to do דריסה *derisa*. וכל *ve-chol*
הדורס *ha-dores* אין *ein* ציפורן *tziporen* נשמטת *nishmetet*, and not only that,
here's additional reason to say it didn't do it, because any animal
that claws, its fingernail does not leave behind. So the fact that
there's a fingernail, you can say like this. Number one, it probably
wasn't through
clawing because fingernails don't come out in the act of clawing. Ah,
you'll say, give me a break, a lion was among oxen, how
did it not claw? No, it doesn't always happen that it claws
either, and if it happened you wouldn't have the fingernail left behind.
So it is reasonable to assume this was not a result of
clawing. וזאת *ve-zos* הואיל *hovei* וציפורן *ve-tziporen* יושבת *yosheves* לו *lo* בגבו
*be-gavo*, since you've got the fingernail sticking out of the back, אימר
*eimar* בכותל *be-kosel* נתחכך *nis-chatech*, it got it through rubbing against a
wall. How did the fingernail get against the wall? So it says,
oh, of course the fingernail came from the lion, the question is
did it come from the lion through an act of clawing? Maybe
the lion was scratching his hand and his fingernail fell off as
a result, and then this fingernail found its way into the back
of this cow. So the point is don't tell me give me
a break, how could that happen, a lion among oxen and you
don't? No. Number one, it's possible not lions don't always attack, and
number two, if it did attack it wouldn't have fallen off, so
it's
reasonable based on the evidence to assume it was not attacked.
Or if it didn't attack there was no דריסה *derisa*.
Yeah, that we're not saying. Okay. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אדרבא *adarabba*, no, say the opposite. Why? נתחכך *nis-chatech* בכותל *be-kosel*
means if
it was דריסה *derisa* then there's no fingernail.
Had there been דריסה *derisa* wouldn't have been the fingernail, so therefore
we know there wasn't דריסה *derisa*.
Wait, why? Why wouldn't he attack and not then poison?
Ah, oh, you, that's what you think, that וכל *ve-chol* הדורס *ha-dores*
means דורס *dores* with the poison. No, because then it wouldn't have
said נתחכך *nis-chatech* בכותל *be-kosel*. So, alright. So now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this: אדרבא *adarabba*, no, say the opposite. רוב *rov*
שוורים *shvarim* מתחככין *mis-chatchin* ומיעוטן *u-mi'utan* אין *ein* מתחככין *mis-chatchin*,
say most oxen will, you know, will rub their backs against
the wall, but some won't. So some oxen won't have gotten contact
with the wall at all. So number one, you can't tell me
oh the ox definitely got in contact with the wall. Some oxen
won't be rubbing their back against a wall, won't have gotten in
contact with the wall at all. Number one. וכל *ve-chol* המתחכך *ha-mis-chatech*
אין *ein* ציפורן *tziporen* יושבת *yosheves* לו *lo* בגבו *be-gavlo*, and even
those that did rub against the wall, you don't get a fingernail
in your back by rubbing against the wall. So you're saying you
don't get a fingernail in your back from a lion that clawed
at you, you don't get a fingernail in your back from rubbing
against the wall, and it's quite possible a, this animal never rubbed
against the wall and b, even if it did it wouldn't have
a fingernail in its back. So the logic is that it didn't
get it that way, and it did get it through being attacked
by the lion. וזאת *ve-zos* הואיל *hovei* וציפורן *ve-tziporen* יושבת *yosheves* לו
*lo* בגבו *be-gavlo* אימר *eimar* ארי *ari* דרסו *deraso*, since it's got
a fingernail in its back, presumably it was attacked by a lion.
So איכא *ika* דאמרי *de-amrei* הכי *hachi* ואיכא *ve-ika* דאמרי *de-amrei* הכי
*hachi*, you can make an argument both ways. Right, there's reason to
say there's the evidence that it was not attacked is that fingernails
don't come out on attack. The evidence that it was... The fact
is, it's got a fingernail in its back. Okay, so you can
make both arguments. איכא למימר הכי ואיכא למימר הכי, אוקמי מילתא אחזקה,
Uki milta achazkeih, so you give it its חזקה. chazakah. An animal
has a חזקה chazakah of being a non-טריפה treifah. unless you have
evidence that it is a טריפה. treifah So here if you have
a ספק safek whether this creates a טריפה treifa, or not, you
give it its חזקה. chazakah. הוי ספק דרוסה, Havai safek drusah, it
is a doubt whether it had the דרוסה drusah act done to
it or not, שרב לטעמיה, she-Rav l'taameih, and Rav goes according to
his reasoning, דאמר אין חוששין לספק דרוסה, d'amar ein chosheshin l'safek drusah,
if there's a doubt whether it was attacked, we don't worry about
it. We assume that, you know, an animal starts its life not
being attacked. So therefore we continue to give it its חזקה, chazakah,
and unless we know it was attacked, we are not concerned.
We could say it the other way, that the animal starts its
life as being בחזקת אינה כשרה, b'chezkat einah kesherah, and so then
here you strengthen the חזקה chazakah of not being כשרה. kesherah.
Yeah, but it is true, you know, once you've שחט shacht it,
that is interesting about how we say that because we do say
מחיים it's בחזקת b'chezkat that it's אסור, assur, but we do say
once it's שחט shacht properly it's חזקת היתר. chezkat hetter. So also
there's always a question about whether you use חזקה chazakah to describe
physical states or do you use חזקה chazakah to describe halachic states.
Because if you use it to describe physical states, you could say
it started its life being a non-דרוסה. drusah If you use it
to describe halachic states, you would say it started its life as
non-כשרה. kesherah. So there is that question about which way you go
with חזקה, chazakah, but the גמרא Gemara is clear that once you've
שחט shacht it, it has a חזקת היתר. chezkat hetter. So, but
I will say, and like the rest, but I will say, you
know, again, it does become strange. On the one hand, you get
all of these crazy things in the גמרא, Gemara you know, on
the one hand, like when they're, even if a hole is covered
up by a membrane, etc., etc., we're still saying that that's not
good enough. You have all of these concerns about these types of
animals and their poison which we don't relate to because we don't
think that that happens. And at the other hand, then you have,
so it seems like the גמרא Gemara is going overboard always being
concerned. And then you have cases where the גמרא Gemara says, eh,
it's a ספק, safek, not a problem, it's חזקת היתר. chezkat hetter.
Now, I will point out though the גמרא Gemara is pretty consistent
about that, meaning where the גמרא Gemara is מחמיר, machmir, it's מחמיר
machmir where it knows it's a problem and it says that something
else won't solve it. Oh, we've got a hole, we're not going
to assume a סירכא sircha solved it, we're not going to assume
a membrane solved it, we're not going to assume this thing solves
it because we know or we assume based on the existence of
a סירכא sircha that there is a hole. Now, we might not
say that's a correct assumption, but in the גמרא's Gemara perspective, that
that is a right assumption that there is a hole. They say
once there's a problem, you can't, we can't assume that you solve
it that easily. Okay, we might not think דרוסה drusah? is a
problem, but the גמרא Gemara thinks it is. As if it's a
problem, it's a problem. Where the גמרא Gemara is pretty consistently מיקל
meikil is when there's a question whether there's a problem at all.
So you have a hole, when did it come? Did it come
before שחיטה shechitah or after שחיטה? shechitah? We have a way of
suggesting it came after שחיטה. shechitah. We'll compare it to other holes,
maybe it's where it was handled by the טבח. tabach. Okay, you've
got this case, was it a genuine דרוסה drusah. or not a
genuine דרוסה? drusa. We'll assume that it was not a real דרוסה.
drusa. So the גמרא Gemara basically says we'll take a more מיקל
meikil approach presumably based on this principle of relying on חזקה chazakah
to assume that this thing happened after שחיטה shechitah or didn't happen
at all and isn't a problem. Once a problem is established, we're
going to be more מחמיר machmir and before we, you know, and
we're not going to be so prepared to say that the problem
has been solved. Okay, so we should just appreciate that these are
not really contradictory approaches. דב, Dov, you had a question.
There was one path the גמרא Gemara doesn't take down and that
is if we have, if there are cases where you have a
fingernail in the back and on the other hand you believe that
cats don't leave fingernails, doesn't that, the one way you could, you
could approach that is saying maybe my assumption about cats not leaving
fingernails.
That is a very good
point. That also goes to a pre-empirical age. You know, we, when
we see evidence otherwise, we revise our assumptions. The גמרא Gemara does
do that sometimes, you know, we cannot make these big global statements.
But generally in a pre-empirical age, you know, where your wisdom and
your knowledge of things comes from sort of authoritative sources and books,
when you see something in the world that doesn't correspond to it,
you just say, oh, that was like, you know, what do they
call it now, experimental error or a, you know, sampling error. That
was just like, that was a weird case. Outlier. Outlier. Meaning remember
what the גמרא Gemara said before about the snake that drank from
the חומץ chometz or whatever, the vinegar or whatever, oh, that was
a stupid snake, right? So they just reject, you know. Now by
the way, anybody that has read this great little book by Kuhn,
the, what's it called,
the something of scientific revolution, it's called The Structure of Scientific Revolutions.
Anyway, he says that this is still how things work, that even
now that we do do studies, whatever, you know, like experiments and
we take evidence and so on on, you know, for a time
you have a certain paradigm and you start seeing anomalies in your
experimental data. So it goes for like a period of years where
people just put them down to experimental error and anomalies until finally
they get to be so much that it forces a paradigm shift
and a revision of our whole basic assumptions. Okay, so but that
was even more true in a pre-empirical age. So you have cases
like what's his name,
Ptolemy, who was the one that wrote the big,
that ancient medical book? Galen. Galen. So Galen's medicine, right? So when
people actually opened up bodies and saw that the anatomy was different
than it was in Galen, they basically said, "Oh, this is a
weird body." Okay. They didn't revise their assumptions about that. So we
do have to appreciate some of those basic differences. Okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. I think it's The Structure of Scientific Revolutions, a highly recommended
book. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אין
חוששין לספק
דרוסה. Ein chosheshin lesafeik drusa.
אמר ביבי Amar Bibi says לא אמרו אלא ציפורן. lo amru ela
tziporen. That's only if you see the fingernail sticking out because then
you say that doesn't happen by attacked, when it's attacked. אבל מקום
ציפורן Aval mekom tziporen if you see a hole which was made
by a fingernail, חוששין, then obviously you're concerned. Of course a lion
went in, you see a hole of a fingernail, right? The whole
leniency here was that the fingernail wasn't, you know, was detached. But
if you just see the hole, so of course you're concerned that
it now is a דרוסה. drusa? וציפורן נמי לא אמרו Ve'tziporen nami
lo amru and even when the fingernail is detached, we only say
that אלא לחה. ela lacha. אבל יבשה אבדא דמשמתא, Aval yevesha avda
demishamta, only if it is moist, you know, a fingernail. But if
it is a dried fingernail, then maybe that actually did fall out
of the lion. Sometimes it will shed its fingernails if they somehow
get dried out. Okay? ולחה נמי לא אמרו Velacha nami lo amru
and when do we say that a moist fingernail is not a
problem? אלא חדא, Ela chada, only one. אבל תרתי ותלת, Aval tarti
ve'tlat, if you see two or three, right? What's the likelihood that
two or three fingernails went right into the back of the cow?
There clearly is evidence of having been clawed. Okay. חיישינן, Chayshinan, that
is a problem. והוא דקיימי בדרדי דכוחפא, Vehu dekaymi bedardei de'chuchpa, that's
if they are sort of in a line of a clawing line,
meaning if they're, you know, lined up nails and in the way
they appear on the animal's hand, like big ones and small ones,
obviously it's evidence of being clawed. Okay. איתמר, Itmar, now, so that's
the issue about ספק דרוסה safeik drusa in a specific case about
a detached fingernail. But now we're going to get to a more
general discussion. רב אמר אין חוששין לספק דרוסה, Rav amar ein chosheshin
lesafeik drusa, if there's a doubt, then we assume a חזקה chazaka
that the animal's okay and we're not concerned about a doubtful דרוסה.
drusa? ושמואל אמר חוששין לספק דרוסה, U'Shmuel amar chosheshin lesafeik drusa, we
are concerned. So now the גמרא Gemara tries to limit the debate.
דכולי עלמא ספק על ספק לא על, De'kulei alma safeik al safeik
lo al, if there's a question whether the animal entered into the
herd or not, whatever the animal is, a lion, a wolf, whatever,
and so on,
not a wolf, what do we say? A, yeah, wolf. Okay, anyway,
if it's a question whether the animal entered into the herd, אימא
לא על, eima lo al, then everybody will agree that we don't
even know it entered into the herd, we'll assume it didn't enter.
Now, this could be with all of these things, you'll see, the
question is, is this a formal issue or a or a percentage
issue? Is it like anything less than, I don't know, thirty percent,
fifty percent or whatever, we're not going to begin to be concerned?
It's not considered legitimate ספק, safeik, you know? What's the chances if
we don't even know if it entered in? So the likelihood that
it did enter and created a problem is very small. So it's
a percentage issue or is it a formal concern? The formal concern
is something that's called in הלכה halachic terminology לידת הספק, leidat hasafeik,
which means that you need a concrete problem that then forces you
to say, "Well, did this did this initial or not?" So if
it's too far removed, it's not even a לידת הספק. leidat hasafeik.
You know, that's kind of somehow they explain the principle of ספק
ספיקא, sfek sfeka, right? A double doubt is on issue. Maybe this
happened and then maybe that happened, maybe it went in and if
it went in, maybe it clawed. So you know, that's like a
ספק ספיקא. sfek sfeka. So even if the percentage might be reasonably
high, if it's a double doubt, it's like doubly removed, you don't
even know that it was there, then that's not enough at a
from a formal level to say that it's a לידת הספק, leidat
hasafeik, a presenting of a problem that forces us to address it.
The problem only presents itself when you know that there was a
lion among the among, you know, among the cows. Okay. So if
we don't even know if it went in, everybody would agree it's
not a problem. Okay. ספק לא על. Safeik lo al. So now
it's ספק כלבא ספק שונרא. safeik kalba safeik shunra. Let's say you
don't know if it was a if it was you something did
go in, but you don't know if it was a dog or
a cat, and it's only problem with a cat, אימא כלבא. eima
kalba. So, so maybe it was a maybe it was a dog
that went in. Again, if you don't know there was the presence
of a cat among the cows or among the, whatever, sheep, then
you don't even know that there's a concrete problem you have to
deal with. Now, so until that I would call that a formal
issue of לידת הספק. leidat hasafeik. Now, but now we get to
something which is a little bit more contextual. Let's take a look.
עיילי ויתיבי בינייהו, Aylei ve'yativi beinei'hu,
let's say the animal
was
על, al, went in, you know a cat went in. עייל ושתיק
ויתיב בינייהו Ayil ve'shasik ve'yativ beinei'hu and it just dwelled among them.
A lion walked in among the cows and they were dwelling in
peace and harmony. So אימא שלמא שוי, eima shalma shavei, maybe they
made peace. Okay. Now you know, it's the it's what is it?
It's the it's the lamb lying down with the, whatever? Lion, right?
So there you go, it's the lamb lying down with the lion.
So רש"י Rashi says, let's look at רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi is
not so metaphorical. רש"י Rashi says like this, רש"י Rashi says עשה
שלום עמהם כדרך כמה חיות שנעשה תרבות וגדלות עם בני אדם ובהמה.
Asa shalom imahem kedererch kama chayot shena'asa tarbut u'gedelot im bnei adam
u'vehema. Sometimes you can, you know, domesticate animals that normally in nature
would attack one another but you can domesticate them to live together.
So maybe these animals figured out how to live together just because
it's there, if there's no sense of violence, that also doesn't create
a problem. Now, קטע רישא דחד מינייהו, kta reisha de-chad mineihu, so
all of this I would say there's not yet a לדעת ספק.
leda'at safek. But here we get to where I would say is
a לדעת ספק. leda'at safek. The lion went in and it sliced
off the head of one of the sheep. Now that one's definitely
a טריפה, treifa that's a נבילה. neveila. Now how about the other
sheep? Okay? So I would say the other sheep is like a
ספק safek whether it attacked the other sheep. So no, it says
ניחמור תיחתי, nichmor tichatei, so maybe I'll say that it got its
anger out and now it left the other sheep alone. That's not
enough of a reason even for שמואל Shmuel to be concerned about
the other sheep.
Is this a case where we can see an injury to the
sheep?
No, we don't see an injury. We just saw a lion went
into a herd of sheep, chopped off the head of one, do
we have to say all the other sheep are ספק דרוסה? safek
drusa? Why would you say that? I mean like because there's a
lion, an attacking lion among sheep. Right, but you don't see, you
see one decapitated sheep,
you don't see the others like...
Wow, that's also true. What?
We don't see like all the other sheep like, you know, dragging...
Okay, well that might be part of the, that might be, that's
part of the reason why even שמואל Shmuel who says we are
concerned for ספק דרוסה, safek drusa, the גמרא Gemara tries to limit
it. What cases create a ספק safek in particular sheep if we
haven't even seen it do anything to this particular sheep?
How much have we got so caught up in like different animals
and דרוסה? drusa Like, you know, if it gets up and walks
around, does that eliminate the problem of the
דרוסה?
drusa No, if it waits twelve months, yes, we'll get to that.
But no, the walking around, no.
Even though we don't see an injury, we'd still be concerned for...
well, that's the whole point, we're not concerned. Even שמואל Shmuel who
says we're concerned about ספק דרוסה, safek drusa, we're trying to limit
the cases that שמואל Shmuel would say you're concerned.
So none of these seem to be an injury.
Really? You don't think it's obvious you've got an attacking lion among
sheep that you don't have to start worrying?
I wouldn't see blood on a white sheep.
Okay. All right, so let's keep on going. So so far the
גמרא Gemara, hasn't contradicted you, it says we're not concerned about these
cases. Let's keep on going. Okay. Now, איהו קא מבעי ואינהו קא
מקרקרן, ihu ka mavaei ve-inhu ka mekarkeran, בעותי קא מבעתי. be-utei ka
meva'atei. Let's say it is roaring and they are lowing or groaning,
so do we say that all of that noise indicates that he's
attacking them? No, we say that they're getting each other afraid. You
know, so it's these are sounds that are being made out of
fear, at the presence of or whatever of each other, but it's
not an indication of attack. There's an interesting little רש"י Rashi that
he says about, he's talking about noises the animals are making, why
does the lion called מבעי mavaei and the sheep called מקרקרן? mekarkeran?
So רש"י Rashi says well, you know, we have different verbs for
different animal noises, and he gives you about five examples in Hebrew
about what word you use: birds chirp and cows moo and sheep,
and sheep, you know, what do sheep do? Baa? Bleat! So anyway
רש"י Rashi gives you different verbs for different animal noises. Anyway, okay,
they're just getting each other afraid. מבעתי אהדדי. meva'atei ahadadei. So none
of those are their concerns here. כי פליגי, ki pligi, when do
they disagree? Top of נ"ג עמוד ב'. nun gimmel amud bet. דאיהו
קא שתיק ואינהו קא מקרקרן. de-ihu ka shatik ve-inhu ka mekarkeran. The
lion is being quiet and the sheep are bleating. So מר סבר
מעשה קא עביד, mar savar maisa ka'avid, the only reason they're bleating,
excuse me, they're baa-ing. So why are they making their baa sounds?
So מר סבר מעשה קא עביד, mar savar maisa ka'avid, the only
reason they're baa-ing is because the lion is obviously up to something
and he's attacking them. ומר סבר במחמת ביעותא הוא דקא עביד. u-mar
savar be-machmat bi'uta hu de-ka'avid. No,
they're just afraid of the presence of the lion, but the lion
is not actually attacking. So again, the גמרא Gemara moved from having
it as a formal debate, what I would say is חזקת היתר,
chezkat heter, לדעת ספק, leda'at safek, do you go by חזקה, chazaka,
do you not go by חזקה, chazaka, and now made it a
very particular case of a lion among the sheep with, with you
know, baa-ing but no sounds, and how do we interpret this very
particular set of circumstances? But obviously it sounded before that not that
way because the גמרא Gemara applied it to other cases, to cases
about like a detached fingernail and so on, that רב's Rav general
disposition is that if you have a doubt you assume no problem,
and שמואל Shmuel says once there's a sufficient reason for doubt, whatever,
however you define, not שמואל, Shmuel, excuse me, and was it שמואל
Shmuel against רב? Rav Yeah, רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. And שמואל
Shmuel says once you have a sufficient reason for doubt we don't
pay attention to the חזקת היתר chezkat heter and it is a
problem and you do have to worry about it. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר אמימר, Amar Amemar, so אמימר Amemar
says הלכתא כוותיה דחוששין לספק דרוסה. hilchata kavatei de-choshishin le-safek drusa. Again,
not in all cases, but in cases similar to the ones we
mentioned where there is sufficient basis for doubt, we are concerned and
we don't just say rely on a
חזקה. chazaka. סו אמר ליה רב אשי לאמימר, So amar lei Rav
Ashi le-Amemar, האי דרב מאי? hai de-Rav mai? What about רב's Rav
position? רב Rav says we go by חזקה. chazaka. So how are
you just סתם stam ruling against him? אמר ליה לא שמיע לי.
Amar lei lo shmia li. Oh, I never heard of רב's Rav
position that you're not worried about it. כלומר, K'lomar, says the גמרא,
Gemara what that really means, 'I didn't hear about it,' לא סבירא
לי, lo sevira li, means I don't agree with it. Okay. So
it's like you say to your kid, you know, 'How come you're
not here? You tell me you're not hearing, I'm just not paying
attention, I'm just like ignoring you, it's not like I'm not hearing
you.' Okay. So anyway, I am here, I'm just not listening. So
anyway, yeah, 'I never heard of his position,' meaning his position just
doesn't make any sense to me. Once there's sufficient enough basis to
say that there's a
possible... or is the way to do a test like sort of
like Michael was saying about to sort of do some you know
to see about the ongoing health of the animal to determine whether
or not it really is דרוסה drusa or not? So until now
we just use the phrase חושש. choshesh. So let's take a look.
ואי בעית אימא Ve'iba'is eima and if you want I'll even go
further and say הדר ביה רב לגבי שמואל. hadar bei Rav legabei
Shmuel. רב Rav even reversed himself in the end רב Rav says
we are concerned for ספק דרוסה. safek drusa. How do you know?
דהיא שרקפא Dehi sharkafa a certain like nest of birds or רש״י
Rashi says a basket of birds ספק דרוסה safek drusa דרוסה drusa
that there was a question whether they had been attacked by an
animal ואתא לקמיה דרב ve'asa lekamei de'Rav and it was brought in
front of רב Rav שדרינהו לקמיה דשמואל shadrinhu lekamei de'Shmuel and he
sent it to שמואל. Shmuel.
I mean who were arguing over these very issues? רב Rav and
שמואל. Shmuel.
Yeah well we said that on the עמוד א amud aleph that
רב Rav said ספק דרוסה safek drusa isn't a problem שמואל Shmuel
said it is.
No I know but why would he send it to the person
who holds that?
That's exactly our point that he reversed himself. So let's take a
look. So שדרינהו לקמיה דשמואל shadrinhu lekamei de'Shmuel he sent it to
שמואל. Shmuel. So what did שמואל Shmuel do? חנקינו ושדינו בנהרא chankinu
veshadinu benahara שמואל Shmuel wanted didn't want anybody to rule against him
so he פוסק'נס paskens that it's all טריפה treifa ספק דרוסה safek
drusa so he he choked them he like strangled them and threw
them into the river so nobody should use them. Okay so well
also you know we had cases before that when people say it
was טריפה treifa they said oh you פסק'ד pasked wrong you have
to pay up and we constantly said the only time you pay
up if you פוסק pasken wrong is if you actually physically take
the animal and feed it to the dogs. So here we see
a case where שמואל Shmuel essentially did that. So I hope he's
right or else he's going to have to pay up. Okay so
anyway so that's what שמואל Shmuel did. Now we know שמואל Shmuel
is going according to his position that ספק דרוסה safek drusa is
a problem. So but the question is why did רב Rav send
it to שמואל Shmuel if רב Rav says ספק דרוסה safek drusa
is not a problem?
ואי סלקא דעתך Ve'isalka daitach לא הדר ביה רב lo hadar bei
Rav לישרינהו lishrinhu let רב Rav say מותר muttar it. So why
did he send it to שמואל? Shmuel? Clearly he reversed himself. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute. אלא מאי הדר ביה? Ella mai
hadar bei? So you if רב Rav did reverse himself לישרינהו lishrinhu
let רב Rav say it's אסור assur why are you sending it
to שמואל? Shmuel? The גמרא Gemara says אלא אתריה דשמואל הוה ella
asrei de'Shmuel hava it was שמואל'ס Shmuel's location. What does that mean?
It was שמואל'ס Shmuel's city. Therefore what? So therefore רש״י Rashi has
two versions. One version רש״י Rashi says is therefore you're right we
don't know that רב Rav reversed whether רב Rav reversed himself or
not. Maybe he didn't reverse himself. Why did he send it to
שמואל? Shmuel? Because it would not be respectful to פוסק pasken against
you know against שמואל Shmuel in שמואל'ס Shmuel's city. So you're right
that story you can't prove anything. If he had reversed himself he
would have פסק'ד pasked one way or the other. So that's just
because it was שמואל'ס Shmuel's city. So forget it רב Rav we
don't know that רב Rav reversed himself. רש״י Rashi has another version
which is quite shocking which is the I know רב Rav reversed
himself because had רב Rav actually פסק'ד pasked that it was that
it was מותר muttar then he even in שמואל'ס Shmuel's city he
wouldn't have sent it to שמואל Shmuel because it would not have
been fair to cause this person a loss of money. So the
concern about the כבוד kavod to the רב Rav of the city
would not have overridden the loss to this person. So therefore if
רב Rav really held it was מותר muttar then he would have
פסק'ד pasked it was מותר muttar even in שמואל'ס Shmuel's city. Only
because he held it was אסור assur then he said oh it's
אסור assur so I'm going to say it's אסור assur שמואל Shmuel
will say it's אסור assur I'll give כבוד kavod to שמואל Shmuel
in שמואל'ס Shmuel's city I'll pass the question off to שמואל. Shmuel.
So that's really quite shocking that this idea that you defer to
the authority of the city which we normally take for granted very
often the גמרא Gemara says אתריה דפלוני הוה asrei de'so and so
hava in one in one version of רש״י Rashi one approach of
רש״י Rashi is that the concern about the loss to the person
asking you the שאלה shayla would have greater weight than deferring to
the honor of the רב Rav of the city so too bad
Rifka isn't here because she's always concerned about the reverse. So here
actually according to that one version but רש״י Rashi in the end
really says no no no if you're in somebody else's city they
always פוסק pasken you always you know defer to them regardless of
how you would פוסק pasken and the פשט p'shat of the גמרא
Gemara. is that רב Rav we don't know if רב reversed himself
or not.
So the whole story is because the
whole right the whole reason he passed it on was because it
was שמואל'ס Shmuel's city and we don't know his own פסק. psak.
So even if I am just I feel you're unjustly or whatever
it is you know you but you know if I unjustly feel
that the local תלמיד חכם talmid chacham is causing a loss of
money I should still send it along to him if I'm in
his location? Right exactly.
Those are the two versions of רש״י Rashi unless you think that
what he's doing is even like a טועה בדבר משנה to'eh bidvar
mishna it doesn't even fall within the range of potential you know
of a of a legitimate פסק psak that's different but if it's
within legitimate פסק psak but just not your פסק psak then you
defer to the authority of the רב of the city. Okay so
now the גמרא Gemara's goes on okay now the גמרא Gemara wants
to understand why שמואל Shmuel had to strangle them. So the גמרא
Gemara says so למה לי למיחנקינהו lamalei lemichkinhu why did he have
to strangle them? לשדינהו הכי בנהרא lishdinhu hachi benahara just throw them
into the river without strangling them so there there's an obvious answer
which is they're birds. דמפרחו וסלקו demafarchu vesalku
because they would fly away and somebody else would eat them and
not know there's a problem. Okay ונשהינהו שנים עשר חודש vinhashyinhu shneim
asar chodesh now it gets interesting. It's a ספק דרוסה safek drusa
here's how about there's a way to test for it. How do
you test for it? See if it lives for twelve months because
we're going to find out later that any animal that's a ספק
טריפה safek treifa if it lives for twelve months you know it's
not a טריפה treifa that the on the assumption that a טריפה
treifah. won't live and just not just won't live but any animal
eventually dies. but won't live out a year. So if an animal
lives out a year, it'll tell you that it wasn't a, that
it wasn't actually a טריפה. treifah. Now, that's going to create a
problem in the ראשונים Rishonim as I told you, because the ראשונים
Rishonim had cases where the animal was a ודאי טריפה vaday treifah
and it lived a year, and that led to a contradiction of
direct observation against the גמרא. Gemara's But in the גמרא's Gemara's world,
that doesn't happen, but a ספק טריפה safek treifah can be tested
to see if it lives out the year. And if it lives
out the year, you know it wasn't a טריפה. treifah. So why
didn't you live out the year? So the גמרא Gemara's says, אתי
בהו לידי תקלה, asi behu lidei takala, that'll lead to, to people
stumbling, meaning maybe one animal you could control, but a basket full
of birds holding onto them for a year, somebody's going to eat
it before the year's out. וליזבנהו לעובדי כוכבים, velizvinehu l'ovdei kochavim, sell
it to non-Jews, at least it won't be a total loss. אתי
לזבוניהו לישראל, asi lizvinehu l'Yisroel, they'll turn around and sell it to
Jews and they won't know that this was a problem. ולחנקינהו ולשדינהו
לאשפה, ul'chankinhu ul'shadinhu l'ashpa,
so why throw it into the river? Why not just strangle them
and throw them into the garbage? So the גמרא Gemara's says, ולטעמיך
נשדינהו לכלבים, ul'taameich nishdinhu l'klavim,
okay, so how about throw it to the dogs? You know, okay,
so anyway, it's a general question about why throw it to the
river. אלא לפרסומי מילתא דאיסורא, ela l'farsumei milsa d'isura, to let it
know that he threw all these things to the river, so everybody
knows, oh my God, did you hear that story? שמואל Shmuel threw
twelve birds, strangled them, and threw them into the river, so everybody
understands that these are problem, that these types of things are problematic,
okay, so that they come to maybe next time this thing happens
they'll make sure to ask a question.
Wait one second. So the question was whether it's a ספק דרוסה,
safek drusa, right? Yeah. So you, you're not, and wouldn't you be
able to just look at the bird and then see if they're
any, whatever it is?
So the גמרא's Gemara's going to discuss that, okay?
So what? It's very strange that he would recommend throwing them in
the river. I mean, why don't you, why don't you kill the
birds and sell the meat to non-Jews?
Oh, because no, they were afraid that the non-Jews would turn around
and sell the meat back to Jews.
But kosher, but who buys the meat?
Oh,
you mean why would I assume, oh, you mean once you can't
see the מקום שחיטה, makom shechita, why would you assume, yeah, I
mean if you just sell the bird then, that's true.
Well, that's the גמרא's Gemara. question. Why not even use it for
dog food? So the answer is, is that this is a makes
more, publicizes that this is a big deal and this is a
problem.
It's curious because in so many cases the גמרא's Gemara very stringent
about not wasting
things.
Right, so I don't know if the גמרא's Gemara recommending it as
a general thing. It's trying to get into שמואל's Shmuel's head. You
know, maybe שמואל Shmuel thought that people were being too lenient, they
were just dismissing, eh, yeah, if it was a real דרוסה drusa.
you would have seen more evidence, this, that, the other thing. That's
the way רש"י Rashi says it.
רש"י Rashi says, see, here
he says that he was afraid that, you know, it's hard to
check for דרוסה drusa and it's not so evident about דרוסה. drusa,
So maybe he felt there was an urgency to publicize the problem,
you know, this one time. I don't know if the גמרא's saying
this is a general policy. Okay, let's go on.
ויהא מה שיהא נמי איידי דקליש זיריה דדובא לא מדמיא ביה ולא
מינכרא, v'yehei mah sheyehei nami idi d'kalish zeiharei d'dova lo madamya bah
v'lo mincra, right, it's not so obvious that there's דרוסה drusa, problems,
so שמואל Shmuel wanted to publicize it. He felt, you know, it
was a one-time thing, it's not saying it's a policy. Okay, let's
go on. ההוא בר אווזא דהוה בי רב אשי. hahu bar avza
d'hava bei Rav Ashi. So there was a certain duck, duck or
a goose. אווזא avza is a goose?
So the בר אווזא, bar avza, the son of a goose.
There's a certain goose that was in the house of רב אשי.
Rav Ashi. על ביני קניא, al beini kanya, it went between the
reeds. נפק אתא כי מימסמס קועי דמא, nafak ata ki mimasmas kovei
d'may,
its neck was bloody. Okay, it went between the reeds and it
came out with a bloody neck. So אמר רב אשי לא אמרן
ספק חבסא ושונרא אימר חבסא, amar Rav Ashi lo amran safek chavsa
v'shunra eimar chavsa, normally we would say if you don't know if
it was a dog or a cat we assume it was a
dog, even according to שמואל, Shmuel, there's not enough basis for it
to say that it's a ספק. safek. הכא נמי ספק קניא ספק
שונרא, hacha nami safek kanya safek shunra, it went between the reeds,
what cut its neck? Was it cut its neck because it cut
it against the sharp reeds or was it cut because there was
a cat among the reeds? So אימר קניא אמחייה, eimar kanya amchayei,
so I'll say that it was a reed that, that hit against
it and therefore there's not enough of a ספק. safek. I don't
know that there was necessarily a cat in the, a cat was
the one that did it.
Yeah, but it could have punctured a whatever it is, you know?
Well, presumably that you can observe and see that it didn't do
that, okay? So again, even though we say ספק safek is a
problem, it has to get to the level of being a serious
enough ספק safek to have to contend with. Okay, אמרי בני רבי
חייא, amrei bnei Rabi Chiya, so בני רבי חייא bnei Rabi Chiya
said, דרוסה שאמרו צריכה בדיקה כנגד בני מעיים. drusa she'amru tzricha bdika
keneged bnei me'ayim. Now here we get to this thing about also
trying to inspect. If an animal was a דרוסה, drusah. you check
opposite the stomach area because we're afraid that the דרוסה, drusah the
poison, now this also explains why poison here is a problem when
normally poison is not a problem for, for טריפה. So I was
saying it was the combination of being clawed plus poison, sort of
hole made by the clawing plus poison, but רש"י Rashi here talks
about the fact that the concern that this type of, particular type
of poison will be more like acid and will go in and
create a hole inside of the animal, okay, so therefore it gets
back into the concern of the normal holes in animals. Okay, so
anyway, so he said you check opposite where the stomach, the intestine
area is, and if you see that it's not red, the skin
isn't red, then you can assume that that area was not poisoned,
and if it was maybe attacked in a different area of the
body, it would not affect the organ. So there's a lot of
חידוש chidush here, no? Number two is
if that if that wasn't in that particular area, even if it
was clawed with this poison, it's not a problem. Now there's a
question between רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosfos does this inspection work only
by a ספק דרוסה safek drusah to get out of the possibility
of ספק safek and think, 'Oh, so since we don't see this,
we assume that it wasn't a דרוסה.' drusah Or דרוסה שאמרו. Drusah
she'amru. I know, or תוספות Tosfos is inclined to say that even
if it's a ודאי דרוסה, vaday drusah, this inspection works. So now
we have ways of getting out of the דרוסה drusah problem, right?
Not like falling off the roof where it's just standing up and
walking around, here you need more, but even by a ודאי דרוסה,
vaday drusah, it can live twelve months, or better, if you inspect
the site where you suspect the דרוסה drusah or there's only a
particular area to inspect and you don't have particular evidence, it's not
a problem. והתם שמואל כלא דרב?
V'hasam
Shmuel k'lo d'rav?
Yeah, so that raises
the
question, what's all those ספק דרוסות safek drusas in the back? So
you know רש"י Rashi says, 'Well, maybe those are certain animals where,
you know, based on the skin and based on the amount of
poison where it's very hard. Maybe sometimes you can't really inspect. You
know, there's not enough way to detect it.' But anyway, here at
least we find that, that really most of the time there's a
way by a ספק דרוסה, safek drusah, even a ודאי דרוסה vaday
drusah to inspect it. So let's take a look. Okay. דרוסה שאמרו
צריכה בדיקה כנגד בני מעיים. Drusah she'amru tzricha bedikah k'neged b'nei me'ayim.
You have to check opposite the enter- the inner- the like stomach
organs, the digestive organs. אמר רב יוסף הא דבני רבי חייא כבר
פירשה שמואל. Amar Rav Yosef ha d'vnei Rabbi Chiya kvar pirsah Shmuel.
That statement of the sons of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya that they
was already said by שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל משום רבי חנינא בן
אנטיגנוס דרוסה שאמרו צריכה בדיקה כנגד בני מעיים. D'amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi
Chanina ben Antignos drusah she'amru tzricha bedikah k'neged b'nei me'ayim. You have
to check opposite the stomach organs. Okay, so you- by the way,
I should also point out that the language here makes it sound
like it's being stricter, not less strict, right? That you have to
check. It's not like a checking helps you solve the problem. It
sounds like it's, you know, worse, that any time you've got a
doubt, you've got to check, and without checking it's אסור. assur. So,
but that's not what we're, you know- again, the way רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosfos read that is the opposite, to be lenient. Even
when you know of דרוסה drusah or have a ספק דרוסה, safek
drusah, checking will get you out of the problem. Okay.
Would you check or you wouldn't check a ספק? safek?
You would check, you would check even a ודאי. vaday. And if
you checked and did not see this evidence, you would say that
it's מותר. muttar. Okay, which is very- a) it's not so משמע
from the language. The language makes it- says it's a demand, not
an option- not an option of getting out of a problem.
It's a demand for a ספק safek where before you could just
assume it was okay.
Oh, but we've been ruling like שמואל Shmuel that ספק safek is
אסור. assur. So like the language here does not sound like it's
a leniency. But that's the way רש"י Rashi and תוספות are both
reading it. Okay. בעי אילפא. Ba'ei Ilfa. So אילפא Ilfa asked, יש
דרוסה לסימנים או אין דרוסה לסימנים? yesh drusah l'simanim o ein drusah
l'simanim? We've been talking about a דרוסה drusah. problem in the area
of the stomach area. How about if there דרוסה drusah. was at
the neck area? Is that a problem? Didn't we say that it's
hard and-? Yeah, so that was by falling. So אמר רבי זירא
הא דבעי אילפא כבר פירשה רב חנן בר רבא, amar Rabbi Zeira
ha d'ba'ei Ilfa kvar pirshah Rav Chanan bar Rava, דאמר רב חנן
בר רבא דאמר רב דרוסה שאמרו צריכה בדיקה כנגד בית החלל כולו
d'amar Rav Chanan bar Rava d'amar Rav drusah she'amru tzricha bedikah k'neged
beis hachalal kulo and top-
not just in front of the area of the organs, but the
entire cavity of the animal. ואפילו בסימנים, Ve'afilu b'simanim,
even by the סימנים, simanim, which is not really the בית החלל,
beis hachalal, but okay. And remember the story before we had by
the duck with the bloody neck. Okay. So בעי אילפא, ba'ei Ilfa,
so אילפא Ilfa asked, סימנים שנדלדלו ברובן מהו? simanim shenidaldelu b'ruban mahu?
This is a totally unrelated question except that it has to do
with סימנים simanim and כבר פירשה. kvar pirshah. When the סימנים simanim
are uprooted from their right place, remember we had that before where
they're not exactly embedded in the skin of the neck, in the
flesh of the neck. How much has to be torn out that
it's a problem? So אמר רבי זירא הא דבעי אילפא כבר פירשה
רבה בר בר חנה. amar Rabbi Zeira ha d'ba'ei Ilfa kvar pirshah
Rabbah bar bar Chana. So you see the thing with the כבר
פירשה kvar pirshah is the theme here. That question you asked somebody
else already explained. דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר שמואל סימנים שנדלדלו
ברובן. D'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Shmuel simanim shenidaldelu b'ruban. When
they're uprooted from their place in the flesh, it has to be
the majority then it's a problem. Okay, back to our issue about
דרוסה. drusah בעי רבי אמי, Ba'ei Rabbi Ami, המרתמא מהו? hamartema mahu?
Let's say it's sort of bloody, the area, what's the story?
The area of-
now we're back to ספק דרוסה safek drusah or דרוסה. drusah? So
let's see the answer. אמר רבי זירא הא דבעי רבי אמי כבר
פירשה רב יהודה. Amar Rabbi Zeira ha d'ba'ei Rabbi Ami kvar pirshah
Rav Yehuda. That question was already explained by רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב בדרוסה עד שיאדים בשר כנגד בני מעיים.
d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav bidrusah ad sheya'adim basar k'neged b'nei me'ayim.
So when you're dealing with actual,
when you're actually have a case of דרוסה drusah. that you see
an animal that actually was clawed, what's the evidence of being clawed?
That the skin is red, and it's red opposite where the inner
organs are. So again the way רש"י Rashi explains this, this goes
back to clarify what does it mean when you check by a
דרוסה? Drusa You check to see is the place of the attack
has it turned like, you know, reddish? And therefore what does that
mean for רש"י? Rashi? For רש"י Rashi says that means, that means
that poison has gone in and it will also go in and
continue to go in and go in into the inner organs and
make a hole in the inner organs. And that's why we're concerned
about the, about the skin opposite where the inner organs are. That's
when there's דרוסה. Drusa, But how about if the animal has like
disease case. So let's take a look at that נתמסמסה, Nitmasmisa, however
נתמסמס Nitmasmeis בשר Basar הבשר רואנו כאילו אינו. Habasar ro'eno k'ilu einu.
So
if the flesh is actually sort of dissolving and bloody and whatever,
then it's as if that flesh has been removed. So meaning it's
not necessarily a problem. Being a דרוסה is from the poison. So
if there's evidence of דרוסה, even if it's just on a little
hole on the outside of the animal's stomach, you assume the poison
went in and went into the inner organs and that's a problem.
Rotting flesh is only a problem where you see the rotting. So
you ask yourself, have this flesh been completely cut away, would the
animal be a טרפה Treifa or not? So sometimes if you cut
away outer flesh of the animal, it's not a טרפה. Treifa. In
some areas, if you cut away outer flesh, like certain areas of
the leg and the thigh and so on, it is a טרפה.
Treifa. So here the answer is, rotting flesh, you look at it
as if the flesh isn't there, and then you determine, would it
be a טרפה Treifa with the flesh there or not? Is it
very clear? Meaning when it's a question of poison, you don't just
say you look at it like it's not there, because who cares
if that outer stomach skin is not there? By poison, once there's
evidence that the poison went in to that place in the stomach,
then it's a problem, because you assume it went all the way
in, into the internal organs, and you've got a problem. With rotting
flesh, you don't worry about the inner organs, you just say, if
the flesh wasn't there, would it be a טרפה Treifa or not.
So let's take a look at the גמרא.
I'm sorry, so now we say the יאדים בשר כנגד בני מעיים,
Ya'adim basar k'neged b'nei me'ayim, do they mean just like the part
really closest to the or like all the way through?
Well, that depends because one language was בני מעיים, b'nei me'ayim, the
other language was כל החלל כולו. kol hachalal kulo. So there's different,
you know, בני מעיים b'nei me'ayim probably means just opposite those digestive
organs, but כנגד החלל כולו k'neged hachalal kulo seems they don't need
to look at the very outside
then, to see if it's red over there.
Oh no, no, you look at the outer skin, but it's the
place where it, where if you went straight into your body, you
would hit the בני מעיים. b'nei me'ayim.
Oh, so it's all the way through in that part. No, it's...
it's thick, like a cow... oh no, no, I think it's just
expecting the outside of the skin. You're not, you're not peeling away
layers. You're just looking at the outside.
And then the other question that's not dealt with, you know, we
talked about like ריסוק איברים, Risuq Eivarim, like, you know, falls from
a roof, let's say like a heavy animal like pounces on it,
but then goes off, not claws it, and like sits on it.
I know...
right... I don't know, I don't know... no... I mean, some of
it you had, you did have about sort of birds being trampled,
but the גמרא did not spell out all of the possibilities. Okay,
so now the גמרא says, היכי דמי נתמסמס, Heichi dami nitmasmeis, what
is this type of like rotting away of the flesh? So אמר
רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע כל שהרופא גודרו ומעמידו על בשר חי.
Amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua, kol she-rofe godro umamido al basar
chai. It's flesh that, if you would bring it to a doctor,
the doctor would cut away the rotting flesh till it got to
healthy flesh. So anytime you've got rotting flesh, the halakhic status of
that is a טרפה, Treifa, I mean, who wants to eat an
animal that had had rotting flesh? But anyway, the halakhic status is
as if that flesh were cut away, would the animal be a
טרפה Treifa or not. Okay. אמר רב אשי כי הוינא בי רב
כהנא אייתי קמנא האי ריאה, Amar Rav Ashi, ki havina bei Rav
Kahana, ayiti kamana hai re'ah, they brought in front of us a
lung, דכי הוה מותבי לה יתבה שפיר, d'chi hava matvei lah yatva
shapir,
if you set it on a table, it would be fine, וכי
הוה מדלי לה, v'chi hava madli lah, if they would lift it
up, הוה... hava... there's different, the exact גרסא, girsa, but anyway, תילכא
ונפלה תילכי תילכי, tilcha v'nafla tilchi tilchi, it would sort of, you
know, decompose or whatever, you know, crumble and little pieces would fall
off. So obviously it was very, you know, the organ was very
rotting and delicate and so on. As long as you didn't touch
it, it was fine. וטרפינא לה, Utarfina lah, and he said it
was a טרפה, Treifa, מדרב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, mideRav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua, from the statement we just said before, that if the
flesh is rotting, and here it's not just the outer flesh but
organ flesh, it's like it's not there. So since a lung that
has a hole in it is not good, and we see that
this lung had rotting flesh that easily on touch would fall apart,
it's like that had already been removed and therefore it's no good.
רב נחמן אמר, Rav Nachman amar, Rav Nachman says, בקוץ עד שתנקב
לחלל, b'kotz ad she-tenakev l'chalal, בדרוסה משיאדים בשר כנגד בני מעיים. bi-drusa
mishe-ta'adim basar k'neged b'nei me'ayim.
If a needle or a, what is it called, a
thorn goes into an animal, if it's just stuck on the outside,
it's not a problem. It has to get all the way through
the stomach wall so that we are concerned whether it got into
an organ, right? So if it's just stuck on the outside, who
cares? Everything gets stuck on the outside. But by being clawed, the
actual claws don't have to pierce all the way through the stomach
wall, all the way through like, not the stomach, the abdomen wall,
right? Because once the claw gets in, it inserts its poison and
then it's a problem. So if it is just about a sharp
object, it's not a problem, עד שתנקב לחלל, ad she-tenakev l'chalal, until
it gets actually into the stomach cavity, into the inner cavity. בדרוסה,
Bi-drusa, if it's attacked by a claw, משיאדים בשר כנגד בני מעיים.
mishe-ta'adim basar k'neged b'nei me'ayim. Even if the claw didn't go all
the way in, if it made the flesh red, that's an indication
of the insertion of poison. רב זביד מתני הכי, Rav Zavid matni
hachi, and Rav Zavid says the following way, בדרוסה משיאדים בשר כנגד
בני מעיים, bi-drusa mishe-ta'adim basar k'neged b'nei me'ayim,
like we just said, בסימנים, bi-simanim, when it comes to actual the
trachea and the esophagus, so there a little redness in the neck
is not a concern, we do say that they're tougher and it
won't affect them as immediately, עד שיאדימו סימנים עצמם, ad she-ta'adimu simanim
atzamam,
the actual trachea and esophagus have to turn red,
not just the outer neck. Okay, so normally we assume if the
outer skin turns red after being clawed, it means the poison. went
in and it's a problem, but by the trachea and the esophagus,
we need to see them turn red. And again, the question is,
is that, can you do this test by even a ודאי דרוסה
Vaday derusah or only a ספק דרוסה? Safek derusah? But we're actually
finding now that this is a way to inspect the animal and
to solve problems is to see if it has these indications.